NROTC/V-12 Collection MS029
Digital Collections and Archives, Tufts University
- NROTC/V-12 Exhibit Materials, 1999 -- 2003; MS029.003; 1.75 Linear Feet
  - Exhibit II, 2000; MS029.003.032.001 (Box 32)
    Labels and photographs from exhibit II. Three folders have been added from the MS029 collection documentation file. A folder titled Background Info contains photocopies collected in preparation for one of the four exhibits. A folder titled Exhibit 1 contains correspondence and photocopies collected in preparation for Exhibit I. Also included is a folder titled V-12/NROTC Exhibit II Research/Doc. To Be Used Photo Copies.
  - Exhibit IV, 2003; MS029.003.033.001 (Box 33)
    All exhibit labels and photographs from exhibit IV. One folder has been added from the MS029 collection documentation file, titled V-12 Exhibit #4 (2002-03). It contains correspondence and photocopies of documents collected in preparation for the exhibit.
  - Exhibit III, 2002; MS029.003.034.001 (Box 34)
    Labels and photographs from exhibit III. All labels and mounted photographs belonging to John Zamparelli were given to him, 3/5/03. Three folders have been added from the MS029 collection documentation file, all of which contain photocopies of documents collected in preparation for the exhibit. The folders are titled: Exhibit 3; V-12 Exhibit 3 - Object List; and Future V-12/NROTC Exhibits
- Photographs, 1908 -- 1999; 1940 -- 1950; MS029.004; 5.3 Linear Feet; 34 Digital Object(s)
  This series contains images of the Navy V-12 Program on the Medford Campus.
  - Tufts College Naval R.O.T.C. on the steps of Cousens Gymnasium (Class of 1945), 1942; MS029.004.035.00001 (Box Shared 46)
    This photograph was found uncatalogued in the stacks in summer 2008. It is located in an oversize box with photographs from other collections. If more photographs in this collection are acquired, they can be combined into a new box.
  - Navy V-12 photomontage, 1943; MS029.004.DO.00318; Unknown (Box Shared 86)
    Image also found in V-12 Scrapbook.
    World War, 1939-1945; Navy V-12 Program; Flags; Trumpet; photographic print
  - 'Colors' on the Hill, 1944; MS029.004.DO.00953; Unknown (Box Shared 74, Box Shared 43)
    mounted on 23 x 17 paper in NROTC scrapbook, page 4.
    World War, 1939-1945; NROTC; Flags; photographic print; copy negative; Navy V-12 Program; Reserve Officers Training Corps (Navy)
  - NROTC/V-12 marching exercises, 1944; MS029.004.DO.00954; Unknown (Box Shared 74, Box Shared 43)
    mounted on 23 x 17 paper in NROTC scrapbook, page 26.
    World War, 1939-1945; NROTC; photographic print; copy negative; Navy V-12 Program; Reserve Officers Training Corps (Navy)
  - 'You must have push,' NROTC/V-12 pushup exercises, 1944; MS029.004.DO.00955; Unknown (Box 4, Box Shared 43)
    mounted on 23 x 17 paper in NROTC scrapbook, page 73.
  - War game, December, 1943; MS029.004.DO.00956; Unknown (Box 4, Box Shared 43)
    mounted on 23 x 17 paper in NROTC scrapbook, page 68.
    World War, 1939-1945; NROTC; photographic print; copy negative; Hahn, Bradley; Navy V-12 Program; Reserve Officers Training Corps (Navy)
  - NROTC/V-12 reading 'Life', 1944; MS029.004.DO.00957; Unknown (Box 4, Box Shared 43)
    mounted on 23 x 17 paper in NROTC scrapbook, page 51.
  - 'Quite early', early NROTC training, 1941; MS029.004.DO.00958; Unknown (Box Shared 74, Box Shared 43)
    mounted on 23 x 17 paper in NROTC scrapbook, page 35.
  - Tufts versus Harvard game at Soldiers Field in Cambridge, Massachusetts, 1945; MS029.004.DO.01613; Unknown (Box 5, Box Shared 43)
    mounted on 23 x 17 paper in NROTC scrapbook, page 110.
    Football; Navy V-12 Program; NROTC; Reserve Officers Training Corps (Navy); photographic print; copy negative; Harvard University
  - Tufts NROTC marches to Harvard football game, 1945; MS029.004.DO.01614; Unknown (Box 5, Box Shared 43)
    mounted on 23 x 17 paper in NROTC scrapbook, page 116.
    Football; Reserve Officers Training Corps (Navy); NROTC; Flags; Marches; photographic print; copy negative; Harvard University
  - Tufts College lacrosse team, spring, 1945; MS029.004.DO.01615; Unknown (Box Shared 43)
    8 x 10 print in V-12 scrapbook, page unknown.
    Lacrosse; Athletics; NROTC; photographic print
  - 'Receiving the ring' at the ring dance, 1908 -- 1944; MS029.004.DO.01617; Unknown (Box 5, Box Shared 43)
    mounted on 23 x 17 paper in NROTC scrapbook, page 103.
    Reserve Officers Training Corps (Navy); Navy V-12 Program; Dances; photographic print; copy negative
  - Student volunteers at Tufts Red Cross drive, 1944; MS029.004.DO.01618; Unknown (Box 4, Box Shared 43)
    mounted on 23 x 17 paper in NROTC scrapbook, page 67.
    Navy V-12 Program; Reserve Officers Training Corps (Navy); Students; photographic print; copy negative; Shea, Edward J.; Nichols, Ralph; Red Cross
  - NROTC color presentation on Alumni Day, 1944; MS029.004.DO.01619; Unknown (Box Shared 111, Box Shared 43)
    Reserve Officers Training Corps (Navy); Navy V-12 Program; Alumni Day; photographic print; copy negative
  - NROTC Visitors' day presentation, 1942; MS029.004.DO.01622; Unknown (Box Shared 74, Box Shared 43)
    mounted on 23 x 17 paper in NROTC scrapbook, page 1.
    Reserve Officers Training Corps (Navy); Navy V-12 Program; Students; Marches; photographic print; copy negative
  - Naval training sign, 1944; MS029.004.DO.01913; Unknown (Box Shared 28)
    Reprint.
    Navy V-12 Program; Signs; photographic print
  - NROTC Delta Tau Delta, 1944; MS029.004.DO.01914; Dwight Davis Photo (Box Shared 116)
    Donor: William Burgess, class President of 1946.
    Reserve Officers Training Corps (Navy); Greek letter societies; photographic print; Delta Tau Delta
  - Phi Epsilon Pi fraternity, 1941; MS029.004.DO.02831; Unknown (Box Shared 40)
    Donated by Jason Samuels, E1945.
    Students; Portraits, Group; Fraternities; photographic print; Samuels, Jason; Phi Epsilon Pi
  - Tufts wrestling team, 1942; MS029.004.DO.02832; Unknown (Box Shared 40)
    Athletics; Wrestling; photographic print; Samuels, Jason
  - Jason Samuels, 1999; MS029.004.DO.02833; Unknown
    Donated by Jason Samuels E1945
    Reserve Officers Training Corps (Navy); Samuels, Jason
  - Sub-Chaser Control 1298, Coat of Arms, 1945; MS029.004.DO.02834; Unknown (Box Shared 29)
    Donated by Jason Samuels, E1945. Sub-Chaser Control-1298 where he was Executive Officer.
    World War, 1939-1945; Submarine chasers; Coats of arms; photographic print; Samuels, Jason; Navy V-12 Program; Reserve Officers Training Corps (Navy)
  - Sub-Chaser Control-1298, Battle Record, 1945; MS029.004.DO.02835; Unknown (Box Shared 29)
    3.5 x. 2.5. Donated by Jason Samuels. Battle Record: invasions to Iwo Jima, Okinawa, Ie Shima, Iheya Rhetto, Aguni Shima; shot down Japanese "Jake" airplane.
    World War, 1939-1945; Submarine chasers; photographic print; Samuels, Jason; Navy V-12 Program; Reserve Officers Training Corps (Navy)
  - Postcard of Miami Beach featuring Jason Samuals at the Sub Chaser Training Center, April, 1944; MS029.004.DO.02836; Unknown (Box Shared 29)
  - Jason Samuels with 2 1/2 inch handlebars and goatee, 1945; MS029.004.DO.02837; Unknown (Box Shared 29)
    3.5 x. 2.5. Donated by Jason Samuels E1945. Image dated July-August 1945. Photo taken at the Naval Base in Subic Bay, Philippine Islands during preparation for invasion of Japan.
    World War, 1939-1945; Navy-yards and naval stations; photographic print; Samuels, Jason; Navy V-12 Program; Reserve Officers Training Corps (Navy)
  - Jason Samuels with Dick Romes and Bob Wehrman at Naval Base in Saipan, Marianas Islands, 1945; MS029.004.DO.02838; Unknown (Box Shared 29)
    Photo dated November, 1945. Donated by Jason Samuels, E1945
  - Sub-Chaser Control-1298 in Okinawa, 1945; MS029.004.DO.02839; Unknown (Box Shared 29)
    Photo dated October, 1945. Donated by Jason Samuels, E1945. Photo of Sub-Chaser Control where he was Executive Officer.
    World War, 1939-1945; Submarine chasers; Navy-yards and naval stations; photographic print; Samuels, Jason; Navy V-12 Program; Reserve Officers Training Corps (Navy)
  - Jason Samuels in dress whites before going to overseas, 1944; MS029.004.DO.02840; Unknown (Box Shared 29)
    World War, 1939-1945; photographic print; Samuels, Jason; Navy V-12 Program; Reserve Officers Training Corps (Navy)
  - Jason Samuels at Tufts graduation, 1947; MS029.004.DO.02841; Unknown (Box Shared 29)
    Photo dated May, 1947. Donated by Jason Samuels, E1945.
    World War, 1939-1945; Commencement; photographic print; Samuels, Jason; Navy V-12 Program; Reserve Officers Training Corps (Navy)
  - Jason Samuels at the Office of Naval Research, Sands Pt., Port Washington, 1946-05; MS029.004.DO.02842; Unknown (Box Shared 29)
    World War, 1939-1945; Birds; photographic print; Samuels, Jason; Navy V-12 Program; Reserve Officers Training Corps (Navy)
  - Jason Samuels, Lt. USNR, 1944; MS029.004.DO.02843; Unknown (Box Shared 40)
    World War, 1939-1945; Reserve Officers Training Corps (Navy); Navy V-12 Program; photographic print; Samuels, Jason
  - V-12 Naval Cadets, Co. 8, 1945; MS029.004.DO.03972; Dwight Davis Photo (Box Shared 19)
    5
    World War, 1939-1945; Students; Men; People; photographic print; Navy V-12 Program; Reserve Officers Training Corps (Navy)
  - Regimental review, 1944; MS029.004.DO.03973; Unknown (Box Shared 19)
    9 x 13
    People; World War, 1939-1945; Flags; Men; photographic print; Navy V-12 Program; Reserve Officers Training Corps (Navy)
  - Naval ROTC Cadets, 1943; MS029.004.DO.03988; Dwight Davis Photo (Box Shared 66)
    7 x 13
    World War, 1939-1945; Men; Students; photographic print; Reserve Officers Training Corps (Navy); Navy V-12 Program
  - Naval ROTC, Company 5, Color Company, June, 1945; MS029.004.DO.03989; Unknown (Box Shared 66)
    8 x 13
    World War, 1939-1945; Men; Students; People; photographic print; Carlson, R. F.; Reserve Officers Training Corps (Navy); Navy V-12 Program
  - Tufts NROTC graduating class, February, 1945; MS029.004.DO.03992; Dwight Davis Photo (Box Shared 66)
    Men; Students; Navy; World War, 1939-1945; photographic print; Reserve Officers Training Corps (Navy); Navy V-12 Program
  - V-12 Co. 6 and American Society of Mechanical Engineers group photographs, 1944 -- 1945; 1959 December; MS029.000186; 0.1 Linear Feet 1 folder (Box 22, Folder 8)
    Gift of Julian P. Mulak Family, 2021, accession UA-2022-006.
    Two 8x10" black and white group photographs. One photograph labeled A.S.M.E. Tufts, Dwight Davis, April 1945, #1, and depicts a mix of students in uniform and not in uniform. Second photograph labeled V-12 Co. 6, Tufts 10-44 and depicts cadets posed outside Cousens Gymnasium.
  - Pete Merenda official Navy portrait, circa 1980; MS029.000187
- Program files, 1996 -- 2011; MS029.005; 1.2 Linear Feet
  This series documents the V-12/NROTC Memorial Fund Program. Records created and compiled by program coordinator Ellie Short include correspondence, meeting minutes, and memos related to fundraising, awards, and the NROTC display case in Tisch Library.
  This series is arranged as received from Ellie Short.
  75 years from the date of creation. 20 years from date of creation.
  - V-12/NROTC Memorial Fund Program Book 1 of 2, [1 of 4], 1997 -- 1998; MS029.005.040.00001 (Box 40)
    75 years from the date of creation.
  - V-12/NROTC Memorial Fund Program Book 1 of 2, [2 of 4], 1997 -- 1998; MS029.005.040.00002 (Box 40)
  - V-12/NROTC Memorial Fund Program Book 1 of 2, [3 of 4], 1998; MS029.005.040.00003 (Box 40)
  - V-12/NROTC Memorial Fund Program Book 1 of 2, [4 of 4], 1998 -- 1999; MS029.005.040.00004 (Box 40)
    20 years from date of creation.
  - V-12/NROTC Memorial Fund Program Book 2 of 2, [1 of 4], 1997 -- 1998; MS029.005.040.00005 (Box 40)
  - V-12/NROTC Memorial Fund Program Book 2 of 2, [2 of 4], 1996 -- 1997; MS029.005.040.00006 (Box 40)
  - V-12/NROTC Memorial Fund Program Book 2 of 2, [3 of 4], 1998 -- 1999; MS029.005.040.00007 (Box 40)
  - V-12/NROTC Memorial Fund Program Book 2 of 2, [4 of 4], 1998 -- 1999; MS029.005.040.00008 (Box 40)
  - Gifts (Binder) 1 of 2, 1998 -- 1999; MS029.005.040.00009 (Box 40)
  - Gifts (Binder) 2 of 2, 1998 -- 1999; MS029.005.040.00010 (Box 40)
  - Correspondence (V-12 Binder, 1 of 6), 1999 -- 2000; MS029.005.040.00011 (Box 40)
  - Display Case Report (V-12 Binder, 2 of 6), 1999 -- 2000; MS029.005.040.00012 (Box 40)
  - Emails and Letters (V-12 Binder, 3 of 6), 1999 -- 2000; MS029.005.040.00013 (Box 40)
  - V-12 List (V-12 Binder, 4 of 6), 1999 -- 2000; MS029.005.040.00014 (Box 40)
  - Meeting Minutes and Agendas (V-12 Binder, 5 of 6), 1999 -- 2000; MS029.005.040.00015 (Box 40)
  - Memos, Requisitions, Pledge Cards, Notices (V-12 Binder, 5 of 6), 1999 -- 2000; MS029.005.040.00016 (Box 40)
  - Ellie's V-12 Folder, 2000; MS029.005.040.00017 (Box 40)
  - Display Case (V-12/NROTC Binder, 1 of 3), 2000; MS029.005.040.00018 (Box 40)
  - Project (V-12/NROTC Binder, 2 of 3), 2002 -- 2003; MS029.005.040.00019 (Box 40)
  - Award (V-12/NROTC Binder, 3 of 3), 1999 -- 2003; MS029.005.040.00020 (Box 40)
  - Art Hirshberg's Photo of Car, 2011; MS029.005.040.00021 (Box 40)
  - Online Exhibit: Tufts Answers the Call to Service, 2007; MS029.005.040.00022 (Box 40)
- Additional accessions, MS029.006; 1 Volumes
  This series contains film reels and plans for a World War II memorial. These materials are unprocessed and may not be available for research. Please contact DCA for more information about access.
  - NROTC V-12, photo and reel of film, MS029-001 (Box 1)
    former barcode 39090011510332g Donations from Peter F. Merenda in Folder 2
  - NROTC World War II Memorial Plans, MS029-003 (Box 2)
    No dates. Plans found uncataloged in stacks in July 2007; includes watercolor of the memorial; additional room available in box.; former barcode 39090014014092g